# 你看 这一排子的竹鼠啊
Look? The bamboo rats in this row
# 都是比较凶的哦
are the more fierce ones.
# 来 排着队来
Come on! Line up!
# 一个一个把你们拎起来
I'll take you all out, one after one
# 拎进去
and put you into the cages.
# 去四川
We're going to Sichuan
# 去四川哦
to Sichuan, you know?
# 很好玩的地方
There's so much fun.
# 你们要不要去哦
Do you guys want to go?
# 不要去是不是 不要去也得去哦
You don't want to go, do you? I don't care. You need to go.
# 你看它站起来啦
Look? It's standing up.
# 肯定很想去
It must be craving for the trip.
# 你看这个竹鼠
Look at this bamboo rat!
# 一动不动的
It's like a statue.
# 肯定很想去四川
It must be craving for the Sichuan trip.
# （缺失）
Right?
# 看 给他们一人带三只过去
Look? I am bringing 3 to each of them.
# 现在这个笼 这里是
Now the cage....here is...
# 下去
Go inside!
# 不愿意下去是不是
You don't want to, do you?
# 不要紧的 去那边玩 又不是干嘛
Come on! It's just a tourist trip, not what you are thinking.
# 还有一只
One more.
# 刚好
All,
# 刚好六只这里
all six are here,
# 加上这个
together with this one.
# 山药怕咬哦
Shyo (another cyberstar) is afraid of being bitten,
# 叫我们帮他杀好
so he asked us to skin and gut them for him,
# 带过去
before bringing to him.
# 王刚的那三只就不用
But the three rats for Wang Gang can be
# 不用杀
can be left
# 他来
for him
# 他来杀
for him to prepare
# 刚刚说被咬 真的被咬了一下
I was just taking about being bitten, and now I am truely bitten by it.
# 我用碘伏擦一下
I'll wipe the wound with some Povidone-iodine.
# 等一下我就先处理它
That guy will be the first one on my list.
# 小心啊
Be careful!
# 好凶啊 现在
They're are very fierce now.
# 它是不会认主人的哦 我跟你说
It won't recognize you as the owner, you know.
# 好像
I think.
# 是啊
Exactly.
# 妈妈
Mama
# 这个好香
It smells good.
# 我都天天养它 天天喂它
I, I take care of it, feed it everyday.
# 一点感情都没有
It doesn't feel even a little bit grateful.
# 前两天还被咬了一口
I was even bitten a couple of days ago.
# 不是吧 是哪一个？
Oh no! Which one?
# 已经被我处理掉了
I've already neutralized it.
# 已经消灭掉了
It's already annihilated.
# 我养它那么久 养了它快一年了
It has been with been for such a long time, almost a year.
# 说咬就咬
But it bit me mercilessly.
# 哎呦 这只这么凶 这只
Ayo! This one is so fierce, this one.
# 好凶啊
Very fierce.
# 是啊
It is!
# 这里怎么搞的这么紧啊
Why did you make it so tight?
# 不扎紧一点 等一下在半路上跑出来
I had to. Otherwise it runs away on the way.
# 跑出来就麻烦了
And that will be a problem.
# 它出来就抓到它
I'll catch it once it's out.
# 这个咬到手 很痛的哦
It really hurts if your hand is bitten.
# 拉不住 它的尾巴拉不住
No I can't, I can't grab its tail.
# 这个怎么那么凶
How come this one is so fierce?
# 诶 出来啦
Eh! It's out.
# 出来一只
One out!
# 准备烧烤架
Let's get the barbecue stand ready.
# 可以可以 没问题
Sure! Sure! No problem!
# 有没有刀
Do you have a knife?
# 刀啊 有啊
A knife? You bet!
# 去拿把刀
I'll get a knife.
# 水 水有没有烧好
Water, have you boiled the water?
# 水烧好啦
Yea, I have!
# 烧好了 好
Awesome!
# 现在这个 好多那细的毛 要用火枪来 喷一下
Now there is still, a lot of tiny hair remains. We'll burn them by a gas torch.
# 这个是它打架的吧 这里
I guess it got a from a fight, right? Here!
# 对 你看 这里打了两个 两个口
Right. Look! The two, two holes, are from a fight.
# 怪不得你
That's why you...
# 太不听话啦 这个
It's too naughty.
# 太凶了嘛这个
It's just too fierce.
# 可以啦
It's alright now.
Ya!
# 你看 用这个喷枪喷的
Look! The gas torch glazed it,
# 跟金黄色的一样
sort of, like, golden yellow.
# 好香哦
It smells good!
# 闻到香味了
We can smell it now.
# 是啊
Exactly!
# 我们用稻草一烧的话就黑不溜秋的
It always becomes as dark as charcoal when we burnt it by straw back at home.
# 下次回去我也要买一把这样的枪
I'll buy one gas torch like this when I get home.
# 嗯
'kay.
# 这个叫喷枪 在菜市场就可以买得到
It's called gas torch. You can easily buy one from a wet market.
# 是吗
Oh really?
# 对 在厨具市场也有
Yep! And also in kitchenware shops.
# 把它清洗一下
I'll have it washed,
# 把内脏去掉
and remove the guts.
# 嗯 好
Oh, yea!
# 来 我来
Come on! I'll do it.
# 要想让他熟得快 就要改刀改得好
You need to cut properly in order to minimize the cooking time.
# 这个竹鼠我觉得就是
I think this bamboo rat, I mean,
# 要 多改几刀 对吧
needs to be cut several more times, right?
# 多搞几刀
Yea! You're right.
# 这里 大腿 还有大腿上
Here, the legs, on the legs too!
# 大腿上多搞几刀
Cut a few more times on the legs.
# 你看 这么厚这个肉
Look! It's so thick here.
# 你喂竹鼠都喂些什么啊
What do you feed the rats with?
# 它 太能吃啦
It's, because it eats too much.
# 我就喂点竹子啊 象草啊
I feed nothing but some bamboo, or elephant grass.
# 体格也太好了吧
It's build is also marvelous.
# 能吃能睡
Eat well, sleep well.
# 还那么凶
And it's still so fierce?
# 是啊
Indeed!
# 不凶的话我也把它留下来了
Otherwise, I wouldn't have taken it with me.
# 就这个地方特别厚
It's really thick here.
# 这个地方
Here.
# 全是瘦肉哦
It's all lean meat.
# 嗯
Ya
# 那个肉好红啊
The meat is very red.
# 看 好厚啊
Look! It's really thick.
# 其他都还好
Other parts are just fine.
# 这样的话 全身都是
Well then, the whole body,
# 全 全身都是那个酱汁啊 都可以浸透全身
I mean the sauce, the sauce can be absorbed by the whole, whole body.
# 要不这大刀来
Do you want a larger knife?
# 刚好割进去啦 割进去啦
It's alright. It's in.
It's in.
# 是好厚啊
It's really thick.
# 对吧 你看 好厚的脸皮啊
Yea, Look! It's thick skinned.
# 好 现在我们腌一下 放点这个姜
Alright! Let's marinate it for a while. Put some ginger
# 这个葱
This is scallion.
# 放点蚝油
Put some oyster sauce.
# 下次你 你也可以放点蚝油 这个
Next time you, you can also put some oyster sauce. It,
# 很入味的这样 入味
it matches well with bamboo rats.
# 你 你们家有没有料酒
You, you have cooking wine here?
# 料酒 料酒用完啦
Cooking wine? I have used up the cooking wine.
# 那个用完啦
Oh really?
# 对呀
Yup!
# 茅台的就没有
And I don't have Maotai.
# 下次 下 下次我寄两瓶给你
I, I'll sent you two bottles next, next time.
# 要得
Merci
# 这不就是料酒嘛
Isn't it cooking wine too?
# 这个
Let me see.
# 但是 但是你
But, but yours
# 不是我们那种 茅台料酒没有
It's not the same as ours.
Yours is Maotai
# 没 你们那种没有
No.
I don't have it here.
# 不是我们那种
It's not the same type.
# 你们那种没有
I don't have that type here.
# 给它按按摩
Give it a massage.
# 按摩一下啊
Right, a massage.
# 放 放旁边去腌着
Put, put it there to keep it marinated.
# 我们去生 我们去生 生火
Let's set, let's set the fire.
# 好
Great!
# 这火有点猛
The fire is a bit too strong.
# 没关系·
Nevermind
# 好啦好啦
Okay, okay okay.
# 好啦
Okay
# 最后送你一程
Here is your final destination,
# 上烤架
the barbecue stand.
# 放 放上来一点 放上来点
Put, put it a bit more forward, more forward.
# 睡上面去
Lay a bit forward.
# 嗯 睡上面一点啊
Yea, lay a bit forward.
# 好 好好好
Alright! 'kay 'kay 'kay.
# 好重啊
It's so heavy.
# 这个
Well...
# 比较大
it's large.
# 好肥
And fat.
# 直接就上架了哦
So I'll put it onto the stand.
# 上架啦
Go ahead.
# 这个可以
It's not bad.
# 哇 像条小猪一样
Wa! It looks like a piglet.
# 我估计最少要烤一个小时
I think it takes at least an hour.
# 比较
It's rather...
# 比较 比较大个
rather, rather large,
# 而且比较厚
and thick.
# 等一下烤一个小时轮流烤
It takes an hour. Let's take turn.
# 我最后烤
I'll be the last one.
# 快烤熟的时候就我来啊
It's my turn when it's almost done.
# 我要跟你抢
No, it's my turn.
# 拉 拉 拉出来的时候将近五斤
It, it, it was almost two and a half kilo when I took it out.
# 五斤左右
Around 2.5 kg.
# 谁让你养那么肥呀 兄弟
How can you let it be that fat, man?
# 它吃得太多啦 不是我养的 其他人都是很苗条的
It's because it ate too much. I didn't do anything. Others are still very slim.
# 就它吃得最多
It ate the most.
# 看来长肥也是一个
It seems that getting fat is also a...
# 是啊 不能太肥
Yea, they shouldn't get too fat.
# 这烤 都 都
It...roast...it's...it's...
# 没有 没有 这是原来我们烧的
No, no worries. It's because we've seared it.
# 哦
I see
# 好吧
Alright.
# 金黄色
Golden yellow.
# 我觉得你要是再多送几只 我都要搞出经验来啦
I think I'll become very experienced if you send me a few more bamboo rats.
# 真的
Really
# 是啊 下次你要做个 做这个竹鼠池嘛
Yea, why don't you make some, some cells for the bamboo rats next time?
# 搞 在 我再搞几只那个竹鼠放在这里养着
To, I mean, you can keep some rats when I send them to you.
# 想吃的时候就去
Whenever you want one, you can...
# 可以啊
Good idea!
# 想吃的时候就直接去拎起来就可以
you can simply take one whenever you want.
# 热烈欢迎 我们这里有的是竹子
Brilliant. We have nothing but bamboo here.
# 是啊 我看这里的竹子多
Indeed. I see that you have no shortage of bamboo.
# 对呀
Yup!
# 可以养个十 十来二十只是没问题
You can easily have a dozen of them.
# 还有很多很多 你看 我们那里全部都是竹子
We still have plenty, plenty. Look! Everywhere is bamboo.
# 对呀 是
Right!
Yea!
# 十几二十只 十只算什么
A dozen, a dozen is nothing.
# 把你们家农场
Your shed,
# 竹鼠场搬过来都行 我觉得
your whole shed can be moved here, I think.
# 现在我们正扩建
We are really expanding.
# 扩建是吧 对
You mean expanding?
Ya!
# 诶 有没有想法在我这边
Have you ever considered keeping
# 多养几只
some of them here?
# 可以呦
Why not?
# （缺失）
I'll look after them.
# 可以 没问题
Sure! No problem!
# 到时候 到时候 到时候 你先把那个池子建好来
Then, then, then, well, build your cells first.
# 额 我们休息会把 轮流来
Why don't we take a break? Let's take turn.
# 你先来 好不
Can you be the first one?
# 我先来 当然是我先来
Sure! I'll be the first one.
# 休息会
Let's take a break.
# 好香啊
It smells good!
# 熟都还没熟 就开始有香味了
It's still raw, but it already smells so good.
# 开始慢慢的变香了
The smell is getting better and better.
# 这个火好快呀
The fire is very efficient.
# 下次烤的时候用这个夹着烤
I'll be also using this press next time.
# 没那么累
It's much less tiring.
# 想它翻面就翻面 转就转
I can flip it whenever I want.
# 这个好吃啊 这个
It's tasty, this one.
# 来 我翻一下
Let me flip it.
# 金黄色的哦
It's golden yellow.
# 漂亮
Pretty!
# 这个真的烤出来跟那个猪一样 我感觉
Roasting it is really like roasting a pig, I think.
# 就像小猪一样
Yea, just like a piglet.
# 乳猪 是啊 对
Baby pig, yea, right!
# 我伯爷说让你
My uncle was wondering whether
# 想想办法 弄 弄个十只八只过来 我们过年啊
you can, well, give us, like ten rats, for the Chinese New Year.
# 这个也没问题
Absolutely no problem.
# 小case
Just a minor case.
# 就是像这么肥的 最爽了
I want those as fat as this one. They are the best.
# 对
RIght!
# 还有比较凶的
I still have several fierce ones.
# 额 凶的给你
Ah! I'll give you the fierce rats.
# 凶的 凶的
Fierce, fierce...
# 凶的也可以 管它凶不凶
Never mind. I don't care.
# 到了我这里都凶不起来了
They just can't be fierce anymore when they're here.
# 是啊 反正你有吃的哦
Sure! You'll have feast on them anyway.
# 对呀 那个不听话的
Exactly! Those who are naughty,
# 打架的那种
those who like fighting
# 对
Yea
# 特别是那个什么
And don't forget those who are...what..
# 心情郁闷的
in depressive mood.
# 翻一下
Flip it.
# 行不行哦
You need help?
# 我就说 每次你烤的都是明火
I just said that you roast on the flame every time.
# 辣不辣的
Is it spicy?
# 有一点点辣
It's a it spicy.
# 呜 好烫
Oh! Very hot.
# 啊
Aaaaa
# 烫不烫
Is it hot?
# 不烫
No!
# 很香的
It tastes good.
# 好了 啊
Alright! Aaaaa
# 这声音你看
Can you hear the sound?
# 脆了
It's crispy.
# 脆
Yup!
# 你看
Look!
# 是有点那 甘甜甘甜的味道
The taste is like, kind of savory sweet.
# 可以啦 我还要吃
Alright!
I want more!
# 等一下 现在还没熟宝贝
Not now. It's still not ready, babe.
# 这下就更快了哦
It's really fast this time.
# 对呀
Yup
# 还有十分钟就可以了 宝贝
I just needs another 10 minutes, babe.
# （缺失）
Be patient.
# 爸爸 嗯 好了没 还有几分钟
Papa!
Yes?
Ready now? How many minutes left?
# 快了啊
Not many
# 还有几分钟
So how many?
# 还有十分钟
Just 10 minutes
# 怎么现在还有几分钟
How can it be?
# 现在还有十分钟
Yea, it's still ten.
# 刚刚她吃了一下 很好吃的
The piece that she just took is very delicious.
# 刚刚那个 隔膜那里
It's right at the diaphragm.
# 是 一烤的话只有那个是
Yea
Upon roasting, it's like
# 那个回甜的哦 那个瘦肉真的是
the after taste, savory sweet. The lean meat is so incredibly marvelous that
# 一口的话 会吃出那个甜味
that could really taste the difference by just a single bite.
# 放辣一点好不好
Shall we make it bit more spicy?
# 没问题
No problem!
# 真的没问题假的没问题
Are you sure?
# 没问题
Very sure!
# 这个辣椒很辣的呦
This chili is really spicy.
# 少放点 少放
Not too much, not too...
# 少放点
Not too much!
# 我们辣椒少放点
Let's have less chili,
# 你们四川辣椒
your chili in Sichuan.
# 你到了四川来 我跟你说这个辣椒
So you're now in Sichuan, you know, our chilli is...
# 可以啦 可以啦 可以啦 可以啦
Enough enough enough enough
# 没有啦 就这一点 没有啦
No more, there's just a bit left, no more.
# 没有就别倒啦 还倒
So what are you doing? You're still putting more.
# 哦 糟了 哦 另一面没放
Oh! Damn it! We've forgotten the other side.
# 没事没事
No no no!
# 这一面有就行了
Just one side is good enough.
# 放孜然
Cummin
# （缺失）
See? I'm more powerful!
# 噫 好香哦
Yea, it smells good!
# 加点这个
Put some, um...
# （缺失）
Soy sauce
# 那这个辣椒全部撒到这边咯
So all chilli is on this side.
# （缺失）
Ah! Put it on this side.
# 还有辣椒粉吗
Is there any more chilli powder?
# 还有没有辣椒面
Any more grounded chilli?
# 没啦
No more.
# 有 有啊 有拿点来快点
Yes, we do have. Bring it here! Hurry up!
# 太辣啦
It's far too spicy.
# 没事 烤的时候它会掉下去的 对对对
No, it isn't. The chilli will slip away.
Yea, yea yea.
# 对
Yeah!
# 烤的时候会辣下去的 掉下去的
It will slip away, fall off.
# 我反正能吃辣
I can have very spicy food.
# 这要多抖一下 把这个辣椒抖掉
I'll shake it, shake off the chili.
# 再刷层油 不然等一下抖掉了
Brush a layer of oil! Otherwise he's going to shake off the chili.
# 很好 很好 很好看
Good! It looks wonderful!
# 好 这边
Alright. Here comes this side.
# 嗯这个 这个孜然
Well, the, the cumin
# 孜然粉
Cumin powder
# 我感觉这是
It seems to me that,
# 这是
it's like...
# 这屁股上撒点
Sprinkle some onto the butt.
# 简直是美味呀 我觉得
a real delicacy, I think.
# 好啦好啦好啦 不要啦 不要那么多、
Enough enough enough. No more. Not too much.
# 没事 烤的时候会往
No worries. When you are roasting it,
# 往下面掉一些
the chili keep will slip off.
# 都闻到了
See? I am chocked.
# 再来搞点油
I'll fetch some oil
# 芝麻 这个是 这个是什么
Is it sesame? What, what it is?
# 那个是花椒
This is Sichuan chili.
# 这是花椒 面
This is Sichuan chili, the minced one.
# 好啦好啦好啦好啦好啦 够啦够啦
Alright alright alright alright, enough enough enough
# 我还没吃饱呢
I am still hungry!
# 还没吃饱
You're still hungry?
# 你吃不吃辣椒？
Do you like spicy food?
# 不吃
Nope.
# 不吃辣椒
No?
# 你看被你爸爸放了那么多辣椒
But you see how much chili your dad have put?
# 它中间的没有辣椒是不是
There's none in the middle, right?
# 有喔
There is!
# 沺沺不能吃了喔你
Tian Tian you can't have it!
# 你咳嗽还没好
You've not yet recovered from your cough.
# 辣了真的是
It's spicy. I mean it.
# 吃花椒把 我记得
I still remember that you like Sichuan chili, don't you?
# 嗯
Sort of.
# 花椒就少放一点好不好 少放点 少放点
Let's have less Sichuan chili, shall we?
Sure, less.
# 这里总共就只有这么一点
We don't have much here anyway, just a bit.
# 这个花椒
This Sichuan chili,
# 花椒粉来的哦
is powder, right?
# 对 来
Yup, come on!
# 烧烤料这个
This is, barbecue sauce.
# 我还好啊 关键摄影小
I'll be fine. The issue is Mr. Camer...
# 这就看的过瘾了 这加了 加了芝麻就更安逸了
I am so excited.
With the sesame, it tastes even better.
# 更好看了
It looks even better.
# 现在烤好了 我们把这个倒出来
So now it's done! We need to put it onto the tray.
# 这样子
How about...
# 哇 这样想得到
Wa, genius!
# 聪明聪明哈哈哈
Smart, smart, ha ha ha
# 开玩笑
You must be kidding.
# 来
Come on!
# 我们端过去嘛
Let's take it over there.
# 端过去
Sure!
# 端过去吃咯
Let's get started!
# 你看
Look!
# 我们的竹鼠
Our, bamboo rat!
# 我们还是 不要说
Shall we...just get started?
# 说太多了 直接吃吧 我好饿啊
Say no more, let's start, I'm starving now.
# 好香
Wonderful!
# 把它翻开 有十个人
Let's open it.
There're ten of us!
# 有十个人怎么数哒
Ten? How did you count the number?
# 二四六七
Two, four, six, sever
# 这大腿
What a thigh!
# 吃不吃
Do you want it?
# 八
Eight!
# 九十
Nine ten
# 谢谢 谢谢 华农哥
Thank you, thank you. Thanks be to Mr. Huanong.
# 你吃大腿还是吃小腿呀
Do you want thigh or calf?
# 大腿
Thigh!
# 伯爷吃这个 你吃的肥腻的吗
Uncle, do you want a more oily part?
# 你来吃 来 你吃这个肥的 来
Come on! This part is fat. Take it! Come on!
# 吃这个
Have this.
# 行行行行
Take it!
'kay 'kay 'kay 'kay
# 还有一个
There's one more.
# 我要吃那个皮
I want the skin.
# 这里吗 嗯
You mean this part?
Yup!
# 是不是很脆
Is it crispy?
# 嗯
Yup!
# 这个
It's...
# 哇 这个好 这个好
Whoa! This is good, this is good!
# 好嫩哦
It's very tender.
# 你看这个
Look! The,
# 这个油哇
the fat is
# 真的是白里 通透啊 这个油
it's really, like, jelly white.
# 是啊
Exactly!
# 而且很香
And the scent is wonderful!
# 可以吃的 这个油你看 沾点这个酱 酱料
It's edible, the fat. Look. With the sauce, the sauce.
# 对
Right!
# 要沾点酱料
It goes well with the sauce.
# 它为 为什么腻嘞 就是因为没有 没有味道16：05
The, the reason that we feel greasy is because the food is plain.
# 嗯
Yup!
# 嗯 像豆腐一样
Well it's just like tofu.
# 你看这个竹鼠 那么大个
Look at this bamboo rat. It's so large
# 被我们全部吃完啦
but we have finished it.
# 这个竹鼠稍微有点 有点胖哦
This rat is rather, rater fat.
# 味道太好啦
It's simply delicious!
# 它
It,
# 就是吃竹子它都能长那么胖
got that fat simply by eating bamboo.
# 它特别能吃 所以我把它带过来 把它处理掉啦
It eats too much. So I brought it here, to get rid of it.
# 好啦 今天的视频到这里啦
Alright! That's all for today.
# 明天我们 还要去钓鱼
We will be fishing tomorrow.
# 明天我们吃点瘦的
Let's have something leaner tomorrow.
# 嗯 好
Yup! Good idea!
# 那个鱼
The fish...
# 鱼炒菜也很好吃
It's tasty when stir-fried with vegetables.
# 对
Yup,
# 可以哦
not bad!
# 好啦
Alrigth!
# 拜拜
Bye~!
# （缺失）
# 大家好 今天来山药家玩
Hi everyone! Today we come to visit Shyo.
# Hello 大家好 我是山药
Hello everyone! This is Shyo.
# 今天这个 村霸说过来要来祸害我们村
Today, the "overlord" is coming to loot our village.
# 我感觉心惊胆战了
I'm so scared now.
# 那个狗干嘛 它一直在叫
What's happened to that dog? It doesn't stop barking.
# 那狗欢迎你啊
It's welcoming you.
# 嗯 应该是欢迎我
Yea, as expected.
# 嗯太欢迎了
Just a bit too much.
# 我们这是 我们去
Well, we are here to,
# 搞荷叶啊
pick some lotus leaves
# 对 我们去搞点荷叶
Yea, we'll get some lotus leaves
# 往哪走
Where should we go?
# 哇 那个鱼
Wa! That fish!
# 鱼在跑
Oiya! The fish is running away!
# 鱼在跳
They're jumping.
# 猛跳
That one is jumping non stop.
# 猛跳 你不要惦记我们家的鱼哦
Non stop. Don't even think about our fish.
# 那个鱼肯定很好吃的 都是吃草的那个鱼
The fish must be very tasty. They feed on grass, the fish.
# （缺失）
Feed on grass?
# 是啊 喔 又在跳
Yea, Oh, it's jumping again.
# 诶 它怎么老是在跳
Eh? Why is it always jumping around?
# 看到你了 不跳能行嘛
Cuz you are here! How can they stop jumping?
# 看到我来了哦 跟我打招呼哦
They can't help saying hi to me when I'm around.
# 今天我们跟山药一起搞竹鼠哦
We'll be be doing the bamboo rats with Shyo today.
# 搞 搞 搞啥
Do, do, do what?
# 竹鼠
Bamboo rats.
# 搞竹鼠
Do the bamboo rats.
# 烤竹鼠
Roast bamboo rat.
# 烧 烧竹鼠
Sear, sear bamboo rat
# 带我们去搞点那个柴
Take me to fetch some firewood,
# 柴火之类的
or anything similar.
# 我们人 人生地不熟
We are, we are stranger here.
# 那 那里有个老哥 家里很多柴 我们去看 去借一点儿
There, over there, there is a guy with a lot of firewood at home. Let's take a look and borrow some.
# 哇 上面还有蜂蜜哦
Wa! There is honey upthere.
# 哪里
Where?
# 这好像 爬不上去啊
It seems, no quite possible to get there.
# 爬不上去
No, you can't.
# 这是山泉水呦
This is spring water.
# 有点甜的
It's a bit sweet.
# 山药
Shyo!
# 要狠一点对它
Treat it tougher!
# 我感觉它在流口水一直看着我
They are looking at me with a drooling mouth!
# 看见我 流口水
They are drooling when they see me.
# 等下它舔你哦
They'll lick you.
# 哇 这个水
Wa! The water,
# 就像冬天 冬天
it's like winter, winter
# 那个冬天泡到水里面一样
when you get into the water in winter.
# 那个冷水已经
The colder water is
# 刺骨头哦
freezing.
# 泡久点会痛的哦
Staying too long is even painful.
# 能不能坚持三分钟嘛
Can you stand three minutes?
# 坚持不了
No way!
# 一分钟
One minute!
# 你这样 一分钟都可能坚持不了
Perhaps you can't stand even one minute.
# 架起来
Build, build it up
# 架一个那个 架那个什么
Build a, you know, build a, how is it called?
# 篝火晚会 篝火晚会哦
Campfire, campfire, right?
# 我们今天晚上来做一下篝火晚会
We'll have campfire today.
# 请勿模仿
Dangerous! Do not imitate!
# 好 我再去搞一点竹子
Alright! I'll get some bamboo.
# 这个很容易
It can hardly...
# 有点湿了
It's too wet.
# 游过去啊
Shall we swim to the other side?
# 我们上这个
We are now on the,
# 山腰上啊 弄点这个 干竹子
on the mountain side to get some, some dry bamboo.
# 这个要用来起火
It's for starting the fire.
# 因为这个干竹子好点火
It's easier with the dry bamboo.
# 你会不会 你会不会弹这个
Can you, can you flick a match?
# 我不会
No, I can't.
# 好 我来学一下
Good! Let me learn it.
# 我来学 来来来
Let me try, come on!
# 这个然后这样子
Put it here, and then...
# 弹嘛
Flick it!
# 断了
It's broken.
# 你这劲太大 你轻一点 温柔一点嘛
You flicked too hard. Be gentle.
# 人家这上面有美女
There is a beauty on it.
# 小了 这劲又小了
Well, it is too gentle.
# 回潮了 回潮
It's soaked, soaked.
# 可不可以
Is that okay?
# 不燃
No.
# 真的潮了
It's really soaked.
# 不燃
I can't make it.
# 这火柴不好用
These matches are no good.
# 燃了 燃了 燃了
It's buring, it's burning.
# 这个 这个应该要烧很久 这个柴
I think, I think the firewood needs a long time to burn.
# 现在把这个竹鼠啊 稍微处理一下
Now let's get the bamboo rat ready.
# 这牙齿是不是要搞
Do we need to get rid of the teeth?
# 这个牙齿不管
No, just leave them here.
# 你看这个刀 好锋利哦
Have a look at this knife. It's really sharp.
# 杀猪刀哦 不跟你开玩笑哦
It's a butcher knife, no kidding.
# 这是杀猪哒
Oh you mean it's a butcher knife?
# 嗯 杀猪的 真的杀猪刀
Yea, it is. It's really a butcher knife.
# 专卖肉的那些 都是用这个
It's used by the butchers, you know.
# 要先把它戳几个洞哦
First we pierce the rat a few times.
# 要不要把它改个花刀
Do you need to cut a few times?
# 改个花刀好入味
The flavour can be better absorbed.
# 切不动
This knife won't cut.
# 没磨坏把
Did you damage it while grindling?
# 那就戳洞把
Well, I'll just pierce it a few time.
# 戳点洞
Pierce it.
# 这个 可能搞不了把
I don't think it works.
# 戳不动的 要用那个
No it doesn't work, you need the...
# 戳不动
Still doesn't work.
# 我看一下
Let me see.
# 这皮
The skin,
# 皮太厚啦
is too thick.
# 诶 可以哦
Eh! It's works!
# 要割 割一点花出来
I'll cut, cut a few times,
# 才能更入味哦
to better absord the flavour.
# 看你这个杀猪刀
Look that this butcher knife.
# 这杀猪刀有点厉害把
Isn't this butcher knife sharp?
# 割了那么久才割了一个
I have spent such a long time cutting only once,
# 一点点口
with a tiny opening.
# 割一下屁股
Let's cut its butt.
# 来 屁股
Come on, the butt.
# 这杀猪刀
This butcher knife,
# 这个杀猪刀平时吃得实在太多了
the butcher knife has really been used too much.
# 可能
Perhaps,
# 比较钝了这个
it's now blunt.
# 还没我们家的菜刀 那么锋利
It's not even as sharp as my kitchen knife at home.
# 割 割不了
It's, it's hard.
# 割大腿上
Cut on the thigh.
# 搞点生姜
Get some ginger.
# 要不要辣椒
Do you want some chili?
# 小米椒
Xiaomi pepper
# 就直接掰进去把
Shall I just put it in?
# 待会儿你手会很烧哦 等下
You hands will get burning hot.
# 很烧啊
Burning?
# 你不知道我们这边小米椒很厉害
Our xiaomi peppers are really fierce, you know?
# 小心手哦
Watch your hands.
# 用这刀
The knife,
# 看上去很锋利
looks very sharp
# 但是割起来
But when you are really using it,
# 纸老虎
it's a paper tiger
# 这个是什么
What is it?
# 我们这 郫县豆瓣
It's our bean paste from Pixian.
# 自制砍酱
Home-made paste.
# 豆瓣酱
Bean paste.
# 没辣椒酱？
No chili sauce?
# 辣椒酱
It's chili sauce.
# 多放点
More!
# 酱油呢
And soy souce?
# 倒一点
Yea, a bit.
# 这什么
What is it?
# 料酒
Cooking wine.
# （缺失）
# 可以啦
Enough, enough
# 好
Alright
# 是不是按摩
Is it a massage?
# 按摩就按摩 你暗示干嘛
Massage means massage. Why are trying to hint?
# 感觉它好乖哦
It seems that it is very nice.
# 一动不动真可爱
It looks so cute when it's not moving.
# 吃坨生姜
Have a pice of ginger!
# 放在这里腌个半个小时
Keep it marinated here for half an hour.
# 让它在这 趴在这里 先睡个觉
Let it lie down, lie down here and have a sleep.
# 然后 然后我们用那荷叶把它搞起来
Then, then we'll wrap it with the lotus leaves.
# 把这个泥倒出来
I'll pour out the mud.
# 倒出来和点水
Pout it out and mix it with water.
# 和点水一起把竹鼠裹起来
Mix it with water and then we can wrap the bamboo rat with it.
# 先找个漂亮的
Get a pretty one first.
# 哪个比较漂亮
Which one is more pretty?
# 荷叶漂亮的 裹里面
The pretty leaves are wrapped inside.
# 太老
It's too old.
# 长麻子了这个
There are dots on it.
# 诶这个 这个漂亮
Eh, this is pretty.
# 上面盖一层
One more layer on top.
# 然后在旁边 一直这样 一直这样
And the two side. And then keep on wrapping, keep on.
# 要裹紧一点
It needs to be tighter
# 这尾巴
The tail.
# 尾巴 进去
Tail, go inside!
# 塞进去
Squeeze it in.
# （缺失）
Now it's becoming,
# 圆润圆润的
round,
# （缺失）
round and fat.
# 像个 大公鸡蛋一样的·
It's like a, a huge cock egg.
# 公鸡蛋
A cock egg?
# 这恐龙蛋
It's a dinosaur egg.
# 鸡蛋
Chicken egg.
# 要不要写个字
Do you wanna write something?
# 写什么字
What do you wanna write?
# 比如
Like...
# 农药呢
"Nongyao" (lit: pesticide) (Shyo is called "Shan Yao" in Chinese)
# 写成农药
You write "Nongyao".
# 农药组合正式出道
Debut of the newly formed group "Nongyao"!
# 还不如写药农
Why not "Yaonong" then?
# 把它抬到这火堆里面去啊
Put it here, onto the flame.
# 开始烧
So it starts cooking.
# 来来来 我们找个铲子
Come, let's get a shovel.
# 待会再去 借点柴
We'll need some more firewood later.
# 老王家借柴是不是
Still borrow from Wang?
# 又去老王家借啊
Wang again?
# 热死啦 热死啦
It's buring, burning!
# 好香啊
It smells good!
# 颜色都
The colour is...
# 哎呦
Ayo!
# 这边都干啦
It's already dried this side.
# 你看 其中一只竹鼠
Look! This is one of the bamboo rats.
# 就已经成了这样
It has gone through a transformation.
# 把你们带出来旅游
You came with me on the tour,
# 回都回不去了
but there's no return.
# 不好意思啊
Please accept my apology.
# 还要再烤一下
It still needs to be roasted for a while,
# 烤干一点更好吃
so that it becomes even drier and tastes better.
# 哎呀 来啦 来啦·
Oya! It's coming, it's coming!
# 好烫
It's too hot.
# （缺失）
It is fully cooked?
# 熟了
Yup!
# 吃个爪
I'll have a claw.
# （缺失）
Um...
# 可以呦
It's not bad!
# 味道很不错
The taste is really not bad.
# 有点辣味这个
It's a bit spicy.
# 这把刀
The knife
# 一人一颗
One each
# （缺失）
# 吃完大补
It gives us strength.
# 还不错哦
Really not bad.
# 嗯可以
Um! Good!
# 好烫哦
It's hot!
# （缺失）
# 没事
Nevermind
# 上次烤的都没那么烫
It wasn't that hot when we roasted it last time.
# 肉拉的起来吗
Can we pull off the meat?
# 来来 你快
Come on! Hurry up!
# （缺失）
Wa!
# 哎呀可以呀
Aya, not bad!
# 沾点这个酱料
With some sauce
# 它有那荷叶的香味
It, it has the scent of the lotus leaves.
# 所以跟荷叶
So, with the lotus leaves,
# 它的味道都融入了竹鼠里面
the flavour of the lotus leaves is absorbed into the bamboo rat.
# 这一块肥肉
This piece of fat.
# 虽然这个竹鼠有点肥啊
Although this bamboo rat is a bit fat,
# 但是不会油腻的哦
but it's not greasy at all.
# 你看山药吃得多香啊
You see how Shyo is enjoying it?
# 它好想
He wants to...
# 这个
That's...
# 好像这竹鼠老婆有点发少了
It seems that this rat did not have enough wives.
# 没运动
So it did not have enough exercises.
# 是 老婆发少了
Yup, not enough wives.
# 回去我要 给它们多发几个老婆
I'll assign more wives to the rest when I get home.
# 这竹鼠真的好吃
This bamboo rats is really delicious.
# 我 吃相不太好
My manner is bad.
# 就先 就这样啦
So, that's it for today.